——valuable experience.
——宝贵的经验
OK, today we're going to start talking about
今天我们要开始介绍
a particular class of algorithms called greedy algorithms.
一类叫做算法的特殊算法
But we're going to do it in the context of graphs.
但我们会涉及一些图论的知识
So, I want to review a little bit about graphs,
所以 我们先回顾一下图的相关内容
which mostly you can find in the textbook in appendix B.
大部分内容可以在课本的附录B里找到
And so, if you haven't reviewed in appendix B recently,
如果你最近没有看过附录B
please sit down and review appendix B.
请静下心来 复习附录B
It will pay off especially during our take-home quiz.
这对你很有帮助 特别是当你做课后小测时
So, just reminder, a digraph,
只是提醒一下 一个Digraph
what's a digraph?
什么是Digraph？
What's that short for?
是什么的简称？
Directed graph, OK?
有向图(Direct + Graph)
Directed graph, G equals (V,E),
有向图G=(V,E)
OK, has a set, V, of vertices.
有一个顶点集合V
And, I always get people telling me that I have one vertice.
总是有人提醒我 如果只有一个顶点
The singular is not vertice; it is vertex, OK?
单数的话是不叫vertice 叫vertex
The plural is vertices. The singular is vertex.
顶点的复数形式为vertices 单数为vertex
It's one of those weird English words.
它也算是英语单词中的一朵奇葩了
It's probably originally like French or something, right?
原来可能是法语或是什么语言吧？
I don't know. OK, anyway,
不知道 也无所谓
and we have a set, E,
有一个集合E
which is a subset of V cross V of edges.
是V叉乘V条边的子集
So that's a digraph.
这是一个有向图
And undirected graph, E contains unordered pairs.
在无向图里 E包含的是无序的顶点对
sorry? It's Latin, OK,
你说啥？ 噢 它是拉丁语
so it's probably pretty old, then, in English.
确实是非常古老的英语
I guess the vertex would be a little bit of
我猜顶点这个单词有可能是
a giveaway that maybe it wasn't French.
一种外来语 但可能不是法语
It started to be used in 1570, OK.
在1570年开始使用
OK, good,
非常好
OK, so the number of edges is,
那么 边的数量是
whether it's directed or undirected, is O of what?
无论有向还是无向 复杂度是多少？
V^2, good.
O(V^2) 很好
And one of the conventions that will have when we're dealing,
在做这类问题时 有一种约定俗成的事情是
once we get into graphs, we deal a lot with sets.
一旦涉及到图 就会有很多集合需要处理
We generally drop the vertical bar notation within O's
我们通常会把大O记法的那两竖线去掉
just because it's implied. It just makes it messier.
因为它已经隐含了这层意思 加上双竖只会更乱
So, once again, another abuse of notation.
这又是一种符号的滥用
It really should be order the size of V^2,
实际上应该是O(|V^2|)
but it just messes up,
但这样很容易混淆
It means, it's just more stuff to write down.
只是要写的东西变多了
You're multiplying these things, and all those vertical bars
你一边要相乘 一边又有两条竖线
Since they don't even have a sense to the vertical bar,
而一般人甚至觉得这两竖线意义不明
it gets messy.
这只会越来越乱
So, we just drop the vertical bars there
所以在大O记法里面
when it's in asymptotic notation.
这里竖线符号可以去掉
So, E is order V^2 when it's a set of pairs,
那么 一对顶点代表一条边 所以|E|=O(V^2)
because if it's a set of pairs,
因为如果它是顶点对的集合
it's at most n choose two,
最多有n选2种组合
which is where it's at most n^2 over 2,
它最大就是n^2/2
here it could be, at most,
所以它最大也就是
sorry, V^2 over 2, here it's at most V^2.
口误了 是V^2/2 所以大O里面是V^2
And then, another property that sometimes comes up is
还有一个有时会用到性质是
if the G is connected, we have another bound,
如果G是连通的 我们就有另一个界限
implies that the size of E
绑定了E的大小
is at least the size of V minus one.
至少是V-1
OK, so if it's connected, meaning,
所以 如果是连通图 那么
what does it mean to have a graph that's connected?
怎么样的图才算是连通图呢？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：...
Yeah, there's a path from any vertex to any other vertex in the graph
没错 对于图里的任意顶点 总有路径可达其它顶点
That's what it means to be connected.
这就是“连通”的意思
So if that's the case, that a number of edges
如果是这种情况 则边的数量
is at least the number of vertices minus one, OK?
至少是顶点数减1
And so, what that says,
所以 这就是说
so one of the things we'll get into,
我们要研究的是
a fact that I just wanted to remind you, is that in that case,
事实上我只是想提醒你们 在这种情况下
if I look at log E, OK, log of the number of edges,
如果计算log E  给边数取对数
that, by this is O of log V.
这种情况下是O(log V)
And by this, is omega of log V.
这种情况是Ω(log V)
So, it's equal to theta of log V.
所以它等于θ(log V)
OK, so basically the number of,
所以 基本上这个数量...
in the case of a connected graph, the number of edges,
在连通图的情况下 边的数量
and the number of vertices are polynomially related.
与顶点的数量是多项式相关的
So, their logs are comparable.
所以它们log值就差不多了的
OK, so that's helpful just to know because
知道这个很有用
sometimes I just get questions later on
因为你日后就会遇到这种问题
where people will say, oh, you showed it was log E
可能有人会说 虽然你证明它为log E
but you didn't show it was log V.
但你没有证明它是log V吧？
And I could point out that it's the same thing.
然而我却能反驳 他们实际上是等价的
So there's various ways of representing graphs in computers,
计算机有很多不同的表示图的方式
and I'm just going to cover a couple of the important ones.
我只讲几个比较重要的
There's actually more. We'll see some more.
实际上还有很多 我们日后会看到更多的
So, the simplest one is what's called an adjacency matrix.
最简单的一个 称为邻接矩阵
An adjacency matrix.
一个邻接矩阵
An adjacency matrix of the graph, G, equals (V,E),
图G=(V,E)的一个邻接矩阵
where, for simplicity,
为简便起见
I'll let V be the set of integers from one up to n,
让V为从1到n的整数集
is the n by n matrix A given by the ij-th at the entry
(邻接矩阵)是一个n乘n的矩阵A 它的第ij项...
is simply one if the edge, ij, is in the edge set
如果边集里存在一条边ij——则A[i,j]=1
and zero if ij is not in the edge set.
如果边ij不在边集里 则为0
OK, so it's simply the matrix where you say,
只是这样一个矩阵
the ij entry is one if it's in the matrix.
如果边(i,j)存在 则第ij项是1
So, this is, in some sense, giving you
这在某种程度上
the predicate for, is there an edge from i to j?
是一个条件判断 判断是否存在一条边从i到j的？
OK, predicate, remember,
好的，条件判断 要记住
is Boolean formula that is either zero or one,
也就是一条布尔公式 非0则1
and in this case, you're saying it's one
在这种情况下 A[i,j]为1
if there is an edge from i to j and zero otherwise.
如果有一条从i到j的边的话 否则为0
OK, sometimes you have edge weighted graphs,
有时候 有些图的边是加权了的
and then sometimes what people will do
那么人们有时会这样处理
is replace this by edge weights.
用边的权重来替换1或0
OK, it will be the weight of the edge from i to j.
它变成了边ij的权重
So, let's just do an example of that
举一个例子
just to make sure that our intuition corresponds
来证明我们的直觉
to our mathematical definitions.
跟我们的数学定义相符
So, here's an example graph.
这是一个图例
Let's say that's our graph.
假设这是我们的图
So let's just draw the adjacency the matrix.
画一下它的邻接矩阵
OK, so what this says: is there's an edge from one to one?
这里是什么：从1到1是否有一条边相连？
And the answer is no.
答案是没有
Is there an edge from one to two? Yes.
从1到2呢？ 有
Is there an edge from one to three here? Yep.
有一条边从1到3？ 有
Is there an edge for one to four? No.
从1到4? 没有
Is there an edge from two until one? No.
从2到1？ 没有
Two to two? No. Two to three? Yes.
2到2？ 没有 2到3？ 有
Two to four? No.
2到4？ 没有
No edges going out of three.
没有边从顶点3出发
Edge from four to three, and that's it.
从4到3的边 是这一条
That's the adjacency matrix for this particular graph.
这就是这个图特有的邻接矩阵
And so, I can represent a graph as this adjacency matrix
所以 我可以用邻接矩阵来表示一个图
OK, when I represent it in this way,
当用这种方式表示时
how much storage do I need?
需要多少存储空间？
OK, n^2 or V^2
n^2或是V^2
because the size is the same thing for V^2 storage,
因为大小跟V^2是一样的
OK, and that's what we call a dense representation.
这就是所说的稠密表示
OK, it works well when the graph is dense.
如果图是稠密的话 它的效果灰常好
So, the graph is dense if the number of edges
图是稠密的也就是说 如果边的数量
is close to all of the edges possible.
很接近最大可能边数
then this is a good representation.
这样的话 稠密表示就很不错
But for many types of graphs, the number of edges
但对于大多数图来说 边的数量
is much less than the possible number of edges,
都会远远少于最大可能边数
in which case we say the graph is sparse.
这种情况我们称图是稀疏的
Can somebody give me an example of a sparse graph?
谁能给出一个稀疏图的例子吗？
A class of graphs:
一类图
so, I want a class of graphs that as n grows,
我想要一类图 在这种图里随着n的增加
the number of edges in the graph doesn't grow as the square,
图内边的数量不会按n^2的比例增加
but grows rather as something much smaller.
其增长速度会相对小得多
A linked list, so, a chain,
一个链表 一条链
OK, if you look at it from a graph theoretically,
理论上 如果从图的角度来看
is a perfectly good example: only n edges in the chain
这会是一个绝佳的例子：只有n条边
for a chain of length n.
存放在一条长为n的链里
So therefore, the number of edges would be order V.
因此 边的数量会是O(V)
And in particular, you'd only have one edge per row here.
这样一来 这里每一行都只有一条边
What other graphs are sparse? Yeah?
还有什么图是稀疏的？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
Good, a planar graph,
很好 平面图
a graph that can be drawn in a plane turns out that
一个只能在平面上画出来的图
if it has V vertices has, and V is at least three,
如果它有V个顶点 而V至少是3
then it has, at most, three V minus six edges.
那么 它最多只有(3V－6)条边
So, it turns out that's order V edges again.
所以 结果还是O(V)条边
What's another example of a common graph?
还有一种常见图的例子是什么？
Yeah, binary tree, or even actually any tree,
没错 二叉树或者是其它任意树
you know, what's called a free tree if you read the appendix,
如果你看过附录 你就知道那叫自由树
A tree that just is a connected graph that has no cycles
树是一种没有环的连通图
OK, is another example.
这是另一个例子
What's an example of a graph that's dense?
稠密图有什么例子？
A complete graph, OK: it's all ones,
完全图 这里全部是1
OK, or if you have edge weights,
好吧 如果边有权重的话
it would be a completely filled in matrix.
这个矩阵会被完全填满
OK, good.
非常好
So, this is good for dense representation.
所以它很适用于稠密表示
But sometimes you want to have a sparse representation
但有时候你想要用稀疏表示
so we don't have to spend V^2 space to deal with all of the,
不想花费V^2的空间来表示
where most of it's going to be zeroes.
因为这里很多地方都是0
OK, it's sort of like, if we know it's zero,
傲娇一下 既然都是0的话
why bother representing it as zero?
人家才不会写得这么麻烦呢~~
So, one such representation is an adjacency list representation.
好的 有一种方法是用邻接表来表示
Actually, adjacency list of a given vertex is the list,
实际上 一个给定顶点的邻接表
which we denote by Adj of V, of vertices adjacent to V.
我们用Adj(V)来表示 它记录了与V相邻的顶点
OK, just in terms by their terminology,
根据它们的术语
vertices are adjacent, but edges are incident on vertices.
顶点之间是邻接的 但边与顶点是关联的
OK, so the incidence is a relation between a vertex and an edge.
所以 关联是指顶点与边之间的爱情
An adjacency is a relation between two vertices.
邻接是指两个顶点之间的羁绊
OK, that's just the language.
这只是叫法不同
Why they use to different terms, I don't know,
为什么会有不同的术语 我不知道
but that's what they do.
这是哲学的问题了
So, in the graph, for example,
举个例子 在这个图里
the adjacency list for vertex one
顶点1的邻接表
is just the list or the set of two three
是包含2和3的链表或者集合
because one has going out of one are edges to two and three.
因为从1出发的边 有一条到2 有一条到3
The adjacency list for two is just three,
2的邻接表只有3
For three is the empty set, and for four, it is three.
3的邻接表是个空集 4的邻接表是3
So that's the representation.
这是这个表示方法
Now, if we want to figure out how much storage
如果想要知道这种表示法
is required for this representation, OK,
需要占用多少存储空间的话
we need to understand how long the adjacency list is.
那就必须先知道这个邻接表有多长
So, what is the length of an adjacency list of a vertex, V?
对于一个顶点V 其邻接表的长度是多少?
What name do we give to that?
我们用什么名词来描述?
It's the degree. So, in an undirected graph,
那就是度 在一个无向图里
we call it the degree of the vertex.
我们称之为顶点的度
This is undirected.
这是无向图
OK, about here, OK.
在这里
So that's an undirected case.
这是无向的情况
In the directed case, OK,
在有向的情况下
actually I guess the way we should do this is say this.
实际上我想这里应该这样写
If the degree, we call it the out degree for a digraph.
我们称之为有向图的出度
OK, so in a digraph,
在有向图里
we have an out degree and an in degree for each vertex.
每个顶点都有一个出度和一个入度
So here, the in degree is three.
这里入度是3
Here, the out degree is two, OK?
这里的出度是2
So, one of the important lemma that comes up is
接下来 我们要讲的一个最重要的引理
what's called the handshaking lemma.
叫做握手引理
OK, it's one of these mathematical lemmas.
它是数学引理之一
And so, it comes from a story.
好的 我讲个故事
Go to a dinner party,
一个晚会派对上
and everybody at the dinner party shakes other people's hands.
每个人都要和其他人握手
Some people may not shake anybody's hand.
有些人可能一个都没握
Some people may shake several people's hands.
有些人可能跟几个人握了手
Nobody shakes hands with themselves.
没有人跟自己握手
And at some point during the dinner party,
在晚会期间的某个时间
the host goes around and counts up how many,
主人环视现场 然后数了数
the sum, of the number of hands that each person has shaken.
每个人握手次数的总和
OK, so he says, how many did you shake?
他一个一个问:你握了几次手?
How many did you shake? How many did you shake?
你握了几次手? 你又握手了多少次?
He adds them up, OK, and that number is guaranteed to be even.
他把这些加起来 总数一定是偶数
OK, that's the handshaking lemma.
这就是握手定理
Or, stated a little bit more precisely,
或者 更精确地说
if I take for any graph the degree of the vertex,
如果对任意图取顶点的度
and sum them all up, that's how many hands everybody shook,
把所有度加起来 也就是所有人握手的总次数
that's actually equal to always twice the number of edges.
实际总是等于边数的两倍
So, why is that going to be true?
为什么这是成立的?
Why is that going to be twice the number of edges?
为什么会等于边数的两倍?
Yeah?
说一下?
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:……
Yeah. Every time you put in an edge,
没错 每次你加入一条边
you add one to the degree of each person on each end.
你在边的每一个端点都加了1的度
So, it's just two different ways
这只是两种不同的
of counting up the same number of edges.
计算边的数量的方法
OK, I can go around, and if you imagine that,
如果你想像一下
that every time I count the degree of the node,
每次我计算一个顶点的度时
I put a mark on every edge.
我都在它每条边上做一个标记
Then, when I'm done,
当我完成时
every edge has two marks on it, one for each end.
每条边都有两个标记 一端一个
OK: a pretty simple theorem.
一个非常简单的理论
So, what that says is that for undirected graphs,
这对于无向图来说
that implies that the adjacency list representation,
它意味着其邻接表表示法
uses how much storage?
会占用多少存储空间?
OK, at most, 2E, so order E, but that's not all.
最多是2E 所以是O(E) 但还没完
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:……
Yeah, so you have to have the number of vertices
对 所以你还必须知道顶点的数量
plus order the number of edges, OK,
加上边的数量阶
whether it's directed or undirected because
无论是有向图还是无向图
because I may have a graph,
因为可能有一个图
say it has a whole bunch of vertices and no edges,
有一堆顶点但是没有边
that's still going to cost me order V, OK?
但它仍要占用O(V)的空间
So, it uses theta of V plus E storage.
所以需要θ(V+E)的空间
And, it's basically the same thing asymptotically.
这两者基本上是互相等同的
In fact, it's easier to see in some sense for digraphs
实际上 对于有向图而言 从某种程度来看更直观
because for digraphs, what I do is I just add up the out degrees,
因为对于有向图 我要做的只是把所有的出度加起来
and that equal to E, OK,
而那会等于E
if I add up the out degrees as equally.
将所有出度都加起来
In fact, this is kind of like it amortized analysis,
实际上这有点类似平摊分析
if you will, a book keeping analysis,
你可以看成是记账分析
that if I'm adding up the total number of edges,
如果我加上所有边的度
one way of doing it is accounting for a vertex by vertex.
一种方法是一个顶点一个顶点地计算
OK, so for each vertex, I basically can take each degree,
对于每个顶点 基本都能得到它的度
and basically each vertex, look at the degree,
然后我们查看每个顶点的度
and that allocating of account per edge,
把它平摊到每条边上
and then ending up with twice the number of edges,
结果刚好是每条边都有2的度
that's exactly accounting type of analysis
这正是记账法分析
that we might do for amortized analysis.
我们可以拿来做平摊分析
OK, so we'll see that.
好的 我们待会儿会看到
So, this is a sparse representation,
这是一种稀疏表示法
and it's often better than an adjacency matrix.
一般都比邻接矩阵要好
For example, you can imagine if the World Wide Web were done
举个例子 你想像一下 如果万维网
with an adjacency matrix as opposed to, essentially,
是用邻接矩阵来表示的
with an adjacency list type of representation.
而不是用邻接表的表示方式
Every link on the World Wide Web, I had to say,
每个万维网的链接 我必须吐槽
here are the ones that I'm connected to,
要连接的站点有这么多
and here are all the ones I'm not connected to.
没有连接的站点有这么多！！
OK, that list of things you're not connected to
那些没有连接的所有站点
for a given page would be pretty dramatically,
将会非常戏剧性地
show you that there is an advantage to sparse representation.
向你展示稀疏表示的一个优点
On the other hand,
另一方面
one of the nice things about an adjacency matrix representation
邻接矩阵表示法的一个优点是
is that each edge can be represented with a single bit,
每条边都能用一个单独的位来表示
whereas typical when I'm representing
然而 反观这边
thing with an adjacency list representation,
如果用邻接表表示法的话
how many bits am I going to need to represent each adjacency?
我需要多少位来表示每个邻接的边?
You'll need order log of V
需要O(log V)
to be able to name each different vertex.
为了表示每个不同的顶点
OK, the log of the number is the number of bits that I need.
log(顶点数)个位来表示一个顶点
So, there are places where this is actually
所以 在某些情况下
a far more efficient representation.
这是一个非常有效的表示方法
In particular, if you have a very dense graph,
尤其是用来表示一张非常稠密的图时
OK, this may be a better way of representing it.
这将会是一种更好的表示方法
OK, the other thing I want you to get,
另一个需要你们理解的是
and we're going to see more of this in particular next week,
在下周我们将会进行更深入探讨
is that a matrix and a graph,
矩阵和图
they are two ways of looking at the same thing.
它们看待同一件事物的两种不同方式
and in fact, there's a lot of graph theory that
实际上 有很多图论专门涉及到
when you do things like multiply the adjacency matrix,
类似邻接矩阵相乘这样的操作
OK, and so forth.
各种各样
So, there's a lot of commonality between graphs and matrices,
所以 图和矩阵有很多共通之处
a lot of mathematics that if it applies for one,
有很多数学知识 当适用于其中一个时
it applies to the other. Do you have a question,
另一个也同样适用 你是有问题想问
or just holding your finger in the air?
还是只是在练一阳指?
OK, good.
好的
OK, so that's all just review.
刚才所讲的只是复习
Now I want to get onto today's lecture.
现在进入今天要讲的内容
OK, so any questions about graphs?
对于图还有什么问题吗?
So, this is a good time to review appendix B.
这是复习附录B的好机会
there are a lot of great properties in there,
里面有很多不错的相关性质
and in particular, there is a theorem that
特别是 里面有一个理论
we're going to cover today that we're going to talk about today,
我们在今天将要介绍到的
which is properties of trees.
它是树的性质
Trees are very special kinds of graphs,
树是非常特殊的一类图
so I really want you to go and look
真诚地希望你们能回去
to see what the properties are.
看一下那些性质是什么
There is, I think, something like six different
那大概是 我想想 有六种不同的
definitions of trees that are all equivalent,
但又等价的树的定义
OK, and so, I think a very good idea
我觉得绝对是物超所值
to go through and read through that theorem.
如果你阅读了那个理论的话
We're not going to prove it in class, but really,
我不打算在课堂上进行证明 但它真心地
provides a very good basis for the thinking that
会给我们今天要讲的内容
we're going to be doing today.
提供一个超棒的思想基础
And we'll see more of that in the future.
日后 我们会学到更多相关内容
OK, so today, we're going to talk about minimum spanning trees.
今天我们要讲到的是最小生成树
OK, this is one of the world's most important algorithms.
这是世界上最重要的算法之一
OK, it is important in distributed systems.
它在分布式系统里尤为重要
It's one of the first things that
这是几乎所有分布式系统
almost any distributed system tries to find
第一个想要解决的问题
is a minimum spanning tree of the nodes
就是找出一棵最小生成树
that happened to be alive at any point, OK?
所有节点在任意时刻都是活跃的
And one of the people who developed an algorithm for this,
某些人们就是为此设计了这个算法
we'll talk about this a little bit later, OK,
这部分稍后会再进行介绍
it was the basis of the billing system for AT＆T
它是AT&T的记账系统的基础
for many years while it was a monopoly.
这么多年来 从未被超越
OK, so very important kind of thing.
它真的非常重要
It's got a huge number of applications.
它有海量的应用
So the problem is the following.
那么 问题是这样的
You have a connected undirected graph, G equals (V,E),
你有一个连通的无向图 G=(V,E)
with an edge weight function, w,
还有一个给边加权的函数w
which maps the edges into weights that are real numbers.
它给每条边都加一个实数的权值
And for today's lecture,
这堂课上
we're going to make an important assumption,
我们将要做一个重要的假设
OK, for simplicity.
为了简单起见
The book does not make this assumption.
这本书里没有做这个假设
And so, I encourage you to look at the alternative presentation,
所以 我诚邀你们来看看另一种方法的演示
because what they do in the book is much more general,
因为书本上的做法更加一般化
but for simplicity and intuition,
但为了简单和直观
I'm going to make this a little bit easier.
我要降低一下难度
We're going to assume that all edge weights are distinct.
我们假设 所有边的权值都是互异的
OK, all edge weights are distinct.
所有边的权值都是互异的
So what does that mean?
这意味着什么
What does that mean that this function, w,
这个w函数意味着什么？
what property does the function, w, have
这个w函数会具有什么特性？
if all edge weights are distinct?
如果所有边的权值都是互异的话？
Who remembers their discrete math?
谁还记得离散数学怎么说？
It's injective.
它是内映射的
OK, it's one to one.
没错 是一对一的
OK, it's not one to one and onto necessarily.
而且它不一定是一对一的满映射
In fact, it would be kind of hard to do that
实际上 这很难做到
because that's a pretty big set.
因为那会是一个很大的集合
OK, but it's one to one.
但它是一对一的
It's injective.
它是内映射的
OK, so that's what we're going to assume for simplicity.
好的 这就是为了简单起见而做的假设
OK, and the book, they don't assume that.
但在书里 我们不做假设
It just means that the way you have to state things is
这也就意味着 你的表述
just a little more precise.
需要更加精确
It has to be more technically precise.
灰常灰常地精确
So, that's the input. The output is a
那么 这是输入 而输出是...
The output is a spanning tree, T,
输出是一棵生成树T
and by spanning tree, we mean it connects all the vertices.
一棵生成树是指 它连接了所有的顶点
OK, and it's got to have minimum weight.
而且权重的总和还必须最小
OK, so we can write the weight of the tree is going to be,
那这棵树的权重就可以写成是...
by that, we mean the sum over all edges that are in the tree
根据定义 它是所有的在这棵树里的边的权值
of the weight of the individual edges.
加起来的总和
so here I've done a little bit of abusive notation,
这里我又滥用了一下符号
which is that what I should be writing is w of the edge (u,v)
也就是 我应该写的是w((u,v))
because this is a mapping from edges,
因为(u,v)指的是一条边
which would give me a double parentheses.
所以这里应该是双重括号
And, you know, as you know, I love to abuse notation.
但你知道 滥用符号神马的最喜欢了
So, I'm going to drop that extra parentheses,
所以 我毫不犹豫地抛弃了一对括号
because we understand that it's really the weight of the edge,
因为我们都懂的 这就是边的权值
OK, not the weight of the ordered pair.
不是顶点对的权值
So, that's just a little notational convenience.
那么 这是取巧的写法
So one of the things, when we do the take-home exam,
有一点要注意 当我们做家庭作业时
notational convenience can make the difference between
这些取巧的写法可能会引起误解
having a horrible time writing up a problem, and an easy time
可能方便一时 也可能毁于一旦
So, it's worth thinking about what kinds of notation you'll use
所以 要三思而后行
in writing up solutions to problems, and so forth.
选择合适的写法来解题
OK, and just in general, a technical communication,
总的来说 交流的艺术就是
you adopt good notation people understand you.
好的表达能使人理解
You adopt a poor notation:
而糟糕的表达
nobody pays attention to what you're doing because
没人会管你做了些什么
they don't understand what you're saying.
因为他们都不知道你在说啥
so let's do an example.
好吧 举个例子
OK, so here's a graph.
这里有幅图
I think for this, somebody asked once
我觉得会有人问我
if I was inspired by biochemistry or something,
这是不是通过有机化学得到的灵感？
OK, but I wasn't. I was just writing these things down,
但它不是 我只是普通的写写而已
So, here's a graph. And let's give us some edge weights.
好的 这有个图 我们给边加一些权值
OK, so there are some edge weights.
好的 这些是边的权值
And now, what we want is we want to find a tree.
现在 我们要做的是找到一棵树
So a connected acyclic graph
一个连通的无环图
such that every vertex is part of the tree.
而且每一个顶点都是树的一部分
But it's got to have the minimum weight possible.
但这棵树的总权值必须是可能的最小值
OK, so can somebody suggest to me
谁能告诉我
some edges that have to be in this minimum spanning tree?
哪些是属于这棵最小生成树的边？
Yeah, so nine, good.
好的 ⑨ 没错
Nine has to be in there because, why?
⑨肯定在里面 为什么
It's the only one connecting it to this vertex, OK?
因为这是唯一连着这个顶点的边 对伐？
And likewise, 15 has to be in there.
同样地 15肯定也是
So those both have to be in.
这两个都是
What other edges have to be in?
还有那些边肯定是的？
Which one? 14 has to be in.
哪条？14肯定是
Why does 14 have to be in?
为什么14肯定是？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
[Prof]:Well, one of 14 and three has to be in there.
[教授]：嗯 14和3之中肯定有一个在里面
I want the minimum weight.
我要的是最小的总权值
The one that has the overall smallest weight.
它必须有全局最小的权值
So, can somebody argue to me that three has to be in there?
谁能反驳说3一定会在里面？
Yeah?
你说？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
[Prof]:That's the minimum of two, which means that if I had a,
[教授]：这是两者的最小值 也就是说如果我
if you add something you said was a minimum spanning tree
如果你给最小生成树里添加的边里
that didn't include three, right,
它不包括3 好吧
and so therefore it had to include 14,
那就一定有14
then I could just delete this edge, 14,
我大可以删掉这一条边14
and put in edge three.
换成边3
And, I have something of lower weight, right?
那我就能有更小的总权值了 对伐？
So, three has to be in there.
所以 3肯定在里面
What other edges have to be in there?
还有什么变肯定在里面？
Do a little puzzle logic.
做一个逻辑小测试
Six and five have to be in there.
6和5肯定在里面？
Why do they have to be in there?
为什么它们肯定在里面？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:……
[Prof]:Yeah, well, I mean, it could be connected
[教授]：对对对 我是说 它可以...
like through this or something.
像这样子连 或怎样
It doesn't necessarily have to go this way.
它不是一定要这样走
Six definitely has to be in there
6肯定在里面
for the same reason that three had to be, right?
跟3在里面的理由一样 对伐？
Because we got two choices to connect up this guy.
因为跟这家伙相连有两种选择
And so, if everything were connected but it weren't, 12,
所以 如果连的是12这条边
I mean, and 12 was in there.
我是说 12在里面
I could always, then, say, well,
我总是可以反驳
let's connect them up this way instead.
我们还是这样连吧
OK, so definitely that's in there.
所以 6肯定在里面
I still don't have everything connected up.
但现在还没全部连完呢
What else has to be in there for minimum spanning tree?
还有哪些边一定会在最小生成树里的？
Seven, five, and eight, why seven, five, and eight?
7 4 还8 为什么是它们？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:……
[Prof]：OK, so can we argue those one at a time?
[教授]：好的 我们可以一个个讨论吗？
Why does five have to be in there?
为什么是5？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:……
[Prof]：OK, so we have four connected components
[教授]：好的 我们有4个连通的顶点了
because we have this one, this one,
因为我们有这条边 这条边
we actually have, yeah, this one here,
实际上我们还有 对了 这条边
and this one, good.
和这条边 不错啊
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]:……
[Prof]：We need at least three edges to connect them
[教授]：我们至少要3条边来把他们连起来
because each edge is going to reduce the connected components by one.
因为每条边都会减少一个要连接的顶点
OK, so we need three edges,
所以我们还要三条边
and those are the three cheapest ones.
而那三条都是最便宜的
And they work.
而且还可行
That works, right?
它们可行 对吧？
Any other edges are going to be bigger, so that works. Good
其他边都会比较大 所以它们可行 好的
OK, and so, now do we have a spanning tree?
那么 现在我们有生成树了吗？
Everything is, we have one big connected graph here, right?
一切就绪 我们有了一个大连通图 对伐？
Is that what I got?
我的也是这样吗？
Hey, that's the same as what I got.
嘿~~我的也是这样
Life is predictable.
我可以做成魔术表演了
OK, so everybody had the idea of what a minimum spanning tree is,
好的 大家都有最小生成树的概念了吗？
out of this, OK, what's going on there?
从这幅图里 我们看出什么？
So, let's first of all make some observations about this puzzle.
我们先来对这问题做一些观察
And what I want to do is remind you
我要提醒你们一下
about the optimal substructure property
关于最优子结构的性质
because it turns out minimum spanning tree
因为实际上 最小生成树
has a great optimal substructure property.
它有最优子结构
OK, so the setup is going to be,
好的 这个前提是
we're going to have some minimum spanning tree.
我们有一个最小生成树
Let's call it T.
我们称它为T
And, I'm going to show that with the other edges in the graph,
而图里的其他的边
are not going to be shown.
我们忽略不画
OK, so here's a graph.
好的 这有一幅图
It looks like the one I have my piece of paper here.
跟我的小抄上的一模一样
OK, so the idea is, this is some minimum spanning tree.
好的 这个思路是 有一棵最小生成树
Now, we want to look at a property of optimal substructure.
我们要观察它的最优子结构的特性
And the way I'm going to get that, is,
我观察的方法是
I'm going to remove some edge, (u,v),
我移除某条边(u,v)
move an arbitrary edge, (u,v), in the minimum spanning tree.
任意地在最小生成树中移除一条边(u,v)
So, let's call this u and this V.
我们把它成为u 它成为v
And so, we're removing this edge.
那儿 我们移除这条边
OK, so when I remove an edge in a tree,
当我从树中移除一条边
what happens to the tree? What's left?
对树有什么影响？还剩下什么？
I have two trees left, OK?
剩下的变成两棵树了
I have two trees left. Now, proving that,
我剩下两棵树 现在要证明
that's basically one of the properties in that appendix,
这基本上就是附录里写的一个特性
and the properties of trees that I want you to read,
这就是我要你们读的其中一个树的特性
OK, because you can actually prove that kind of thing
因为你们实际上可以证明它
rather than it just being obvious, which is, OK?
而不是看上去很显然是 你懂的
OK, so we remove that.
好的 我们移除它
Then, T is partitioned into two subtrees.
然后 T被分成了两棵子树
And, we'll call them T_1 and T_2.
我们把它称为T_1 和 T_2
So, here's one subtree, and here's another subtree.
这是一棵子树 这是另一棵
We've partitioned it.
我们把它分割开来了
No matter what edge I picked,
不管我选的是哪条边
there would be two subtrees that it's partitioned into.
它都会被分割成两棵子树的
Even if the sub tree is a trivial subtree,
即使那棵子树很小
for example, it just has a single node in it and no edges.
举个例子 它可能只有一个顶点而且没有边
So, the theorem that we'll prove
我们要证明的定理
that demonstrates a property of optimal substructure.
它阐述了最优子结构的特性
T_1 is a minimum spanning tree for the graph, G_1
T_1是图G_1的最小生成树
a subgraph of G induced by the vertices in T_1.
（G_1是）一个由T_1的顶点所导出的图G的子图
OK, that is, V_1 is just the vertices in T_1
也就是说 V_1是集T_1中的顶点
is what it means to be induced.
这就是导出的意思
OK, so V_1 is the vertices in T_1.
V_1是T_1的顶点
So, in this picture, I didn't label it.
但在这图里 我没有这样标记
This is T_1. This is T_2. In this picture,
这是T_1 这是T_2 在这幅图里
these are the vertices of T_1.
这些是T_1的顶点
So, that's V_1, OK?
这是V_1 好吧？
And, E_1 is the set of pairs of vertices, x and y,
E_1是顶点对的集 而x和y则是
that are the edges that are in E_1
E_1里面的边
such that both x and y belong to V_1.
这样一来 x和y都属于V_1
OK, so I haven't shown the edges of G here.
我还没把G的所有边都画出来
But basically, if an edge went from here to here,
但基本上 如果边是从这到这
that would be in the E_1.
它都是属于E_1的
If it went from here to here, it would not.
如果是从这到这 就不是了
And if it went from here to here, it would not.
如是从这到这 也不是了
So the vertices, the graph...
那么这些顶点 这个图...
the subgraph induced by the vertices of T_1
这个由T_1的顶点导出的子图
are just those that connect up things in T_1,
它把T_1里的顶点都连了起来
and similarly for T_2.
同理 T_2也一样
So, the theorem says that
那么 这个定理说
if I look at just the edges within the graph here, G_1,
如果我只观察图G_1里面的边
those that are induced by these vertices,
它们是由这些顶点导出的
T_1 is, in fact, a minimum spanning tree for that subgraph.
实际上 T_1是这个子图的最小生成树
That's what the theorem says.
这个定理就是这样子的
OK, if I look over here conversely, or correspondingly,
好的 相反地 或者说相应地 如果我观察这一边
if I look at the set of edges that are induced
如果我观察这一些由这些顶点
by this set of vertices, the vertices in T_2,
由T_2中的顶点所导出的边
in fact, T_2 is a minimum spanning tree on that subgraph.
实际上 T_2是这边这个子图的最小生成树
OK, we can even do it over here.
我们甚至可以试一下
If I took a look, for example, at these,
让我们看一看 例如这些
let's see, if we cut out some edge like five,
如果我们试着把这个边5砍掉
Let's say we cut out five and if I cut out edge five,
比方说我们砍掉了5这条边的话
that T_1 would be these four vertices here.
那T_1就由这四个顶点组成
And, the point is that
然而 重点是
if I look at the subgraph induced on that these edges here.
如果我观察由这些边所导出的子图
In fact, the six, eight, and three are all
实际山 这个6、8和3的边
edges in a minimum spanning tree for that subgraph.
它们全都是这个子图的最小生成树的边
OK, so that's what the theorem says.
那么 这就是这个定理所说的
So let's prove it.
我们来证明一下
OK, and so what technique are we going to use to prove it?
好的 我们要用什么方法来证明？
OK, we learned this technique last time:
我们之前学到过这个技巧
hint, hint.
爱心小提示
It's something you do it in your text editor all the time:
你们平时做文本编辑是经常会用到的
cut and paste, good, cut and paste.
剪贴法 很好
OK, so the weight of T I can express as
好的 T的权值我可以表示为
the weight of the edge I removed,
我移除的边的权值
plus the weight of T_1, plus the weight of T_2.
加上T_1的权值 加上T_2的权值
OK, so that's the total weight.
那么 这就是总权值
So, the argument is pretty simple.
那么 这个论证很简单
Suppose that there were some T_1 prime
假设存在某个T_1'
that was better than T_1 for G_1.
它比T_1更适合图G_1
Suppose I had some better way of forming a spanning tree.
假设我有一些更好的生成树
then I would make up a T prime,
那我就能得到一棵T'
which just contained the edges, (u,v),
它包含了边(u,v)
and T_1 prime, union T_2.
并上T_1' 在并上T_2
So, I would take, if I had a better spanning tree,
所以 我会取 如果我有一棵更好的生成树
a spanning tree of lower weight for T_1.
它比T_1有更低的权值
And I call that T_1 prime.
我把它成为T_1'
I just substitute that and make up a spanning tree
我只要把它替换掉 然后重建一棵新的生成树
that consisted of my edge, (u,v),
并上这一条边(u,v)
whatever works well for T_1 prime and whatever works well for T.
对T_1’有效的话 那对T也一样有效
And, that would be a spanning tree.
那我们就会有一棵新的生成树
And it would be better than T itself was for G,
而它则会比T更适合图G
OK, because the weight of these is just as the weight for this,
因为这些权值就像这些一样
I now just get to use the weight of T_1 prime,
只是现在 我把它替换成T_1'的权值
and that's less.
而且它更小
And so, therefore, the assumption that
这样一来 我们的假设
T was a minimum spanning tree would be violated
T是最小生成树这个命题就矛盾了
if I could find a better one for the subpiece.
如果我能找到一个更好的子树的话
So, we have this nice property of optimal substructure.
所以 我们得到了这个最优子结构的特性
OK, I have subproblems that exhibit optimal,
我们的子问题会是最优化的
if I have a globally optimal solution
如果对于整个问题来说
to the whole problem within it,
我们有全局最优解的话
I can find optimal solutions to subproblems.
那我们就能找到子问题的最优解
So, now the question is, that's one hallmark.
那么 现在的问题是 这是一个标志
That's one hallmark of dynamic programming.
动态规划的标志
What about overlapping subproblems?
那重叠子问题呢？
Do I have that property?
会不会有这个特性？
Do I have overlapping subproblems over here
对于这类问题 我们会不会有
for this type of problem?
重叠子问题的特性？
So, imagine, for example, that I'm removing different edges.
试想一下 例如 我移除了几条不同的边
I look at the space of taking a given edge, and removing it.
我先观察一下 选出一条边 把它移走
It partitions it into two pieces,
然后树就分成两半
and now I have another piece. And I remove it, etc.
而现在 我选择了另一条边 移除它 等等
Am I going to end up getting a bunch of
我这样做的话 会不会到最后
subproblems that are similar in there?
我会有一堆相似的子问题？
Yeah, I am.
肯定会
OK, if I take out this one, then I take out,
如果我取出的是这一条 我把它移走
say, this one here, and then I'll have another tree here and here.
这一条的话 我就会得到这一棵和这一棵子树
OK, that would be the same as
然而 结果会是一样的
if I had originally taken this out, and then taken that one out.
如果我先取出的是这条 然后再取出这条
If I look at simple ordering of taking out the edges,
如果我只是简单地改改取出的顺序
I'm going to end up with a whole bunch of overlapping subproblems.
那么我会得到一大堆重叠的子问题
Yeah, OK. So what does that suggest we use as an approach?
好的 这说明我们要怎么做？
Dynamic programming, good.
动态规划 很好
What a surprise!
太阳从西边掉下来了
Yes, OK, but
没错 但是..
yes, you could use dynamic programming.
你当然可以用动态规划
But it turns out that minimum spanning tree
但隐藏剧情是 这个最小生成树
exhibits an even more powerful property.
它还有一个更强大的特性
OK, so we've got all the clues for dynamic programming,
我们虽然已经集齐了所有动态规划的条件
but it turns out that there's an even bigger clue
但实际上 这还有一个更强大的隐藏条件
that's going to help us to use an even more powerful technique.
可以触发隐藏剧情 开启这个更为强大的技术
And that, we call, the hallmark for greedy algorithms.
这就是 贪心算法的标志
And that is, we have a thing called the greedy choice property,
我们获得了一个贪心选择的属性
which says that a locally optimal choice is globally optimal.
它指的是 一个局部最优解也是全局最优解
And, of course, as all these hallmarks
当然 就像所有标志一样
is the kind of thing you want to box, OK,
我们都想把它框起来
because these are the clues that you're going to be able to do that.
因为这是你可以应用某算法的证据
So, we have this property
那么 我们得到了这个属性
that we call the greedy choice property.
我们称之为贪心选择属性
I'm going to show you how it works in this case.
我会告诉你们它的原理
And when you have a greedy choice property,
当你有了贪心选择的属性时
it turns out you can do even better that dynamic programming.
实际上你做的会比动态规划还要好
so when you see the two dynamic programming properties,
当你看到这两个动态规划的条件时
there is a clue that says dynamic programming, yes,
这首先说明你可以动态规划
but also it says,
但它同时也说
let me see whether it also has this greedy property
我们不如试下能不能用贪心属性？
because if it does, you're going to come up with
如果能 那你就得到了
something that's even better than dynamic programming,
比用动态规划更好地方法了
So, if you just have the two,
所以如果有这两个条件
you can usually do dynamic programming,
通常你都会用动态规划
but if you have this third one,
但如果你有这第三个属性
it's like, whoa! Jackpot!
你就要喊：哥要超神了！
So here's the theorem we'll prove to illustrate this idea.
这个是阐述了这一思想的定理
Once again, these are not,
再有 这并不是
all these hallmarks are not things that are heuristics.
这些标志并不是什么启发式
I can't give you an algorithm to say,
我不会给你一个算法 然后说
here's where dynamic programming works,
这个能用动态规划
or here's where greedy algorithms work.
这个能用贪心算法
But I can sort of indicate when they work,
我只是告诉你 它们的结构会是这样子
the kind of structure they have.
如果它们能用得上的话
OK, so here's the theorem.
好的 接下来是定理
So let's let T be the MST of our graph.
设T为我们的图的MST
And, let's let A be any subset of V,
令A是V的任意子集
so, some subset of vertices.
也就是 顶点的子集
And now, let's suppose that edge (u,v) is the least weight edge
现在 我们假设边(u,v)是 连接着A到A的补集
connecting our set A to A complement, that is, V minus A.
也就是V-A的 有着最小权值的边
Then the theorem says that (u,v) is in the minimum spanning tree.
那么这个定理就说 边(u,v)属于最小生成树
So let's just take a look at our graph over here
我们先观察一下我们的图
and see if that's, in fact, the case.
然后看看 实际上 这种情况下
OK, so let's take,
我们取...
so one thing I could do for A is just take a singleton node.
我们可以对A做的一件事是 取一个单元素点
So, I take a singleton node,
那我选一个单元素点
let's say this guy here, that can be my A,
假设是它 它是我们的A
and everything else is V minus A.
然后其他所有顶点都属于V-A
And I look at the least weight edge
我观察最小权值边
connecting this to everything else.
连接这一点和其他所有点的边
Well, there are only two edges that connect it to everything else.
好吧 这有两条边连接它和其他的点
And the theorem says that
这个定理是说
the lighter one is in the minimum spanning tree.
这个小一点的边 它属于最小生成树
Hey, I win.
好吧 我赢了
OK, if you take a look, every vertex that I pick,
如果你观察一下 我选哪个顶点都好
the lightest edge coming out of that vertex
从这个顶点出来的最小的那条边
is in the minimum spanning tree.
就属于最小生成树
OK, the lightest weight edge coming out,
对 就是外连的权值最小的边
but that's not all the edges that are in here.
但这并不是这里所有的边
OK, or let's just imagine,
我们可以试想一下
let's take a look at these three vertices
我们观察这三个顶点
connected to this set of vertices.
它们和这一个顶点集相连
I have three edges is going across.
我们有三条连接的边
The least weight one is five.
权值最小的是5
That's the minimum spanning tree.
它就属于最小生成树
Or, I can cut it this way.
或者 我可以这样划分
OK, the ones above,
上面这一个
the edges going down are seven, eight, and 14.
从上面下来的边有 14、8和7
Seven is the least weight.
7是最小的
It's in the minimum spanning tree.
它属于最小生成树
So, no matter how I choose,
无论我选的是哪一个
I could make this one in, this one out....
选这个 不选这个……
take a look at what all the edges are.
再看看所有的边里面
Which ever one to the least weight:
哪个的权值是最小的
it's in the minimum spanning tree.
那个就在最小生成树里
So, in some sense, that's a local property
某种程度上 它是一个局部性质
because I don't have to look at what the rest of the tree is.
因为我不用管树的其他部分
I'm just looking at some small set of vertices if I wish,
我只要看到一小部分顶点就好
and I say, well, if I wanted to connect that set of vertices
我说 好吧 如果我要把这个顶点集
to the rest of the world, what would I pick?
连接到外面的世界去 我选哪一条边好？
I'd pick the cheapest one. That's the greedy approach.
我会选最便宜的那条边 这就是贪心的做法
It turns out, that wins, OK,
结果是 它做到了
that picking that thing that's locally good for that subset, A,
给子集A选择局部最优的边
OK, is also globally good.
对全局也是最优的
OK, it optimizes the overall function.
它是一种全局的优化
That's what the theorem says,
这就是这个定理要说的
So, let's prove this theorem.
那么 我们来证明它吧
Any questions about this?
有没有问题？
let's prove this theorem.
我们来证明它吧
So, we have (u,v) is the least weight edge connecting A to V minus A.
那么 边(u,v)是连接A到V-A的权值最小的边
So, let's suppose that this edge, (u,v),
我们假设这条边(u,v)
is not in the minimum spanning tree.
它不属于最小生成树里
let's suppose that somehow there is a minimum spanning tree
我们假设 有个最小生成树不知怎的
that doesn't include this least weight edge.
没有把最小权值边包含进去
OK, so what technique you think will use
那么 我们要用什么技巧
to prove to get a contradiction here?
来证明它是矛盾的？
Cut and paste, good.
剪贴法 很好
Yeah, we're going to cut paste.
耶 我们要用剪贴法
OK, we're going to cut and paste.
我们要来剪一剪 粘一粘
So here, I did an example. OK, so --
这里 我举个例子 好的
ChuChuChuChuChu
Vv_绝对♂冷冻气_vV
OK, and so I'm going to use the notation.
好的 我要用到这种画法
I'm going to color some of these in.
我要把一些点涂白
OK, and so my notation here is this is an element of A,
好的 我这里的画法是 这是属于A的元素
and color it in.
而涂成白色的那些
It's an element of V minus A.
则是V-A的元素
OK, so if it's not colored it, that's an A.
如果没有上色 它就属于A
This is my minimum spanning tree. Once again,
这是我的最小生成树 再有
I'm not showing the overall edges of all the graphs,
我这里不会把所有的边都画出来
but they're there, OK?
但它们是存在的 好吧？
So, my edge, (u,v), which is not my minimum spanning tree I say,
那么边(u,v) 我们说过它不属于最小生成树
let's say is this edge here.
假设就是这一条边
It's an edge from u, u as in A, v as in V minus A.
它是从u  u在A里面  到v  v在V-A里面
OK, so everybody see the setup?
大家都看到这设定了吧？
So, I want to prove that
那么 我要证明
this edge should have been in the minimum spanning tree,
这条边本应是在最小生成树里的
OK, that the contention that this is a minimum spanning tree,
论点就是 这是最小生成树
and doesn't include (u,v) is wrong.
它没包含(u,v)是错的
So, what I want to do, that, is
我要做的是
I have a tree here, T,
我这儿有一棵树T
and I have two vertices, u and v, and in a tree,
然后我有两个顶点 u跟v 在这棵树里
between any two vertices there is a unique, simple path:
两个顶点之间有一条唯一的 简单的路径
simple path meaning it doesn't go back
简单的路径是指它不会往回走
and forth and repeat edges or vertices.
或者不断地重复某条边或顶点
OK, there's a unique, simple path from u to v.
好的 它是u跟v之间唯一的 简单的路径
So, let's consider that path.
我们考虑这条路径
OK, and the way that I know that that path exists is because
我之所以知道这条路径存在是因为
I've read appendix B of the textbook, section B.5.1,
我看过书里的附录B的B.5.1节
OK, which has this nice theorem about properties of trees.
它介绍了一些很不错的树的性质
So that's how I know that there exists a unique, simple path.
所以我知道这存在一条唯一的 简单路径
So now we're going to do is take a look at that path.
我们现在要做的是观察这一条路径
So in this case, it goes from here, to here x3
在这种情况了 它从这里 到这里x3
And along that path, there must be a point
在这条路径上 肯定存在一点
where I connect from a vertex in A to a vertex in V minus A.
使得我能连接A的顶点到V-A的顶点
Why? Well, because this is in A. This is in V minus A.
为什么？ 因为这是在A里面 这是在V-A里面
So, along the path somewhere, there must be a transition.
所以 这条路径的某处 肯定有过渡点
OK, they are not all in A, OK,
这条路不都是在A之中的
because in particular, v isn't.
因为 v就不是
OK, so we're going to do is swap (u,v)
我们要做的是 把边(u,v)
with the first edge on this path
跟这条路径中的第一条
that connects a vertex in A to a vertex in V minus A.
连接A和V-A的边交换
So in this case, it's this edge here.
在这里 也就是指这一条边
I go from A to V minus A.
我从A到V-A要经过它
In general, I might be alternating many times,
一般来说 可能会存在很多条过渡边
OK, and I just picked the first one that I encounter.
但我只是选择我碰到的第一条
that this guy here. And what I do is I put this edge in.
也就是这一条 我要做的就是拿这条替换它
So then, what happens?
然后会发生什么？
Well, the edge, (u,v), is the lightest thing connecting
好吧 边(u,v)是连接A跟V-A的
something in A to something in V minus A.
权值最小的边
So that means, in particular,
这意味着 在这种情况下
it's lighter than this edge, has lower weight.
它比这条边的权值要小
So, by swapping this,
这样一交换
I''ve created a tree with lower overall weight,
我们就得到一棵有更小总权值的树
contradicting the assumption that
这跟我们的假设矛盾了
this other thing was a minimum spanning tree.
这才是真正的最小生成树
OK: so, a lower weight spanning tree than T results,
所以 一个比T的权值更小的生成树
and that's a contradiction,
矛盾了
How are we doing? Everybody with me?
怎么样？大家跟得上吗？
OK, now we get to do some algorithms. Yea!
现在我们要实现这个算法了 来吧
So, we are going to do an algorithm called Prim's algorithm.
我们要用一种叫Prim的算法来实现它
Prim eventually became a very high-up at AT＆T
Prim现在在AT&T里混得风生水起
because he invented this algorithm for minimum spanning trees,
正因为他发明了这个算法来实现最小生成树
and it was used in all of the billing code for AT&T for many years.
AT&T所有的计帐代码都用了它好多年
He was very high up at Bell Labs
他在贝尔实验室里位高权重
back in the heyday of Bell Laboratories.
而且那时还是在贝尔实验室的全盛时期
OK, so it just shows, all you have to do is invent an algorithm.
这个故事告诉我们 只要发明一个算法
You too can be a president of a corporate monopoly.
你也能成为垄断巨头里的人参赢家
Of course, the government can do things to monopolies,
当然 政府迟早会反垄断
but anyway, if that's your mission in life,
但无论如何 它都是你一生的主线任务
invent an algorithm.
骚年去创造算法吧！
OK, so here's the idea.
下面是它的思路
What we're going to do is we're going to maintain
我们要做的是
V minus A as a priority queue.
把V-A维护成一个优先队列
We'll call it Q.
我们称它为Q
And each vertex, we're going to key each vertex in Q
Q里的每一个顶点 我们都赋一个键值给它
with the weight of the least weight edge,
那就是连接V-A和A之间的
connecting it to a vertex in A.
权值最小的边的权值
So here's the code.
下面是伪代码
So, we're going to start out with Q being all vertices.
一开始 Q包含了所有的顶点
So, we start out with A being, if you will, the empty set.
我们一开始把A设成是空集 根据个人喜好
OK, and what we're going to do it is the least weight edge,
因为我们要求的是权值最小的边
therefore, for everything in the priority queue
因此 优先队列里的所有权值
is basically going to be infinity
一开始都会设成正无穷
because none of them have any edges.
因为A和V-A之间没有边相连
The least weight edge to the empty set is going to be empty.
到空集的权值最小边为空
And then, we're going to start out with one guy.
接着 我们从一个顶点开始
We'll call him S,
我们称它为S
which will set to zero for some arbitrary S in V.
我们会从V中任意选一点S 设为0
And then, the main part of the algorithm kicks in.
然后就是算法的主体
So that's our initialization.
这是我们的初始化步骤
OK, when we do the analysis,
好的 在做分析时
I'm going to write some stuff on the left hand side of the board.
我会写些东西在左手边的黑板上
So if you're taking notes, you may want to also leave
如果你要记笔记的话 你可能也要
a little bit of space on the left hand side of your notes.
在你笔记本的左边预留一点点的空间
So, while Q is not empty,
所以当Q不为空集时
we get the smallest element out of it.
我们从中取出最小的元素
And then we do some stuff.
然后再进行其它操作
That's it.
就是这样
And the only thing I should mention here is,
这是我唯一要说的一点
OK, so let's just see what's going on here.
让我们看一下 这里具体是怎样的
And then we'll run it on the example.
之后我们会用一个例子来演示
OK, so what we do is we take out the smallest element
我们要做的 是每次都从队列里
out of the queue at each step.
取出最小元素
And then for each step in the adjacency list, in other words,
然后对于每一步 在邻接表里 换句话说
everything for which I have an edge going from v to u,
对于所有从v到u的边
we take a look, and if v is still in our set V minus A,
如果v仍属于集合V-A的话 我就进行查看
so things we've taken out are going to be part of A.
所以 取出来的元素就成为了A的一部分
OK, every time we take something out,
每次取出元素时
that's going to be a new A that we construct.
都会构成一个新的A
At every step, we want to find,
在每一步 我们都想找出
what's the cheapest edge connecting that A to everything else?
哪一条是连接A到其它点的最便宜的边？
We basically are going to take whatever that cheapest thing is,
基本上 我们就是取所有最小权值的边
OK, add that edge in,
把边加入这里
and now bring that into A and find the next cheapest one.
把它放入A 然后再找下一个权值最小的边
And we just keep repeating the process.
持续重复这个过程
OK, we'll do it on the example.
举一个例子来说明
And what we do, is every time we bring it in, I keep track of,
我们要做的就是 每次加入一条边时
what was the vertex responsible for bringing me in.
我都追踪哪一个是相关的顶点
And what I claim is that at the end,
我要声明的是 在最后
if I look at the set of these pairs that I've made here,
当我观察这个顶点对的集合时
V and pi of V, that forms the minimum spanning tree.
V还有π[V]就组成了最小生成树
So let's just do this.
我们来演示一下
And, what's that? We're all set up.
这是什么？我们已经画过一次了
So let's get rid of these guys here
那就擦掉这些点
because we are going to recompute them from scratch.
因为我们要在这张草图上重新进行计算
So you may want to copy a new thing over in here,
你们可能要重新画个新的图
copy the graph over again in your notes.
在你的笔记上再画一个新的
I was going to do it, but it turned out,
我其实也打算这么做 但结果表明
this is exactly the board is going to erase this.
擦掉这些点之后 这正是我要的板图
OK, well let me just modify it.
好了 我们再来修改它
OK, so we start out. We make everything be infinity.
一开始让所有顶点都是无限的
OK, so that's where I'm going to keep the key value.
这是我记录键值的地方
OK, and then what I'm going to do is find one vertex.
接下来 我们要做的是找一个顶点
And I'm going to call him S.
把它称之为S
And I'm going to do this vertex here.
我们取这个顶点
We'll call that S.
称之为S
So basically, I now make him be zero.
然后 把它变为O
And now, what I do, is I execute extract min.
现在要做的是 执行取出最小值
So basically, what I'll do is I'll just shade him like this,
那基本上 我会给它加个阴影 像这样
indicating that he has now joined the set A.
表示它现在加入了集合A
So, this is going to be A.
所以 这个表示集合A
And this is element of V minus A.
这是集合V-A里的元素
So then what we do is we take a look at...
接下来 我们要观察一下
We extract him, and then for each edge in the adjacency list,
取出这个点 然后对于它邻接表里的每条边
OK, so for each vertex in the adjacency lists,
对于它邻接表里的每个顶点
that these guys here, OK,
也就是这些顶点
we're going to look to see if it's still in Q,
我们看看它是否仍在队列Q里
that is, in V minus A.
即集合V-A
And if so, we are going to,
如果还在 那我们就要
and its key value is less than what the value is at the edge there
而且如果它的键值还要小于这条边的权值
we're going to replace it by the edge value.
那我们就用边值取代其键值
So, in this case, we're going to replace this by seven.
所以在这个例子里 我们就用7来替换它
We're going to replace this by 15,
用15来替换它
and we're going to replace this by ten,
还有用10替换它
because what we're interested in is, what is the cheapest?
因为我们感兴趣的是最小的权值
Now, notice that everything in V minus A,
现在 注意到所有V-A里的元素
that is, what's in the priority queue, everything in there,
也就是优先队列里面所有顶点
OK, now has its cheapest way of connecting it
现在 它们都有一条最便宜的路径
to the things that I've already removed,
跟被我们移除的点相连
the things that are in A.
也就是A里面的点
OK, and so now I just, when I actually do that update,
那现在我要做一步更新操作
there's actually something implicit going on in this priority queue.
实际上 这个优先队列里有一个隐含的操作
And that is that I have to do a decreased key.
那就是降低键值的操作
So, there's an implicit decrease of the key.
这隐含了一个降低键值操作
So, decreased key is a priority queue operation
降低键值是一个优先队列的操作
that lowers the value of the key in the priority queue.
它会减小优先队列里的键值
And so, that's implicitly going on
所以 这也隐式地影响到了
when I look at what data structure I'm going to use
我会要选用什么数据结构
to implement that priority queue.
来实现这个优先队列
So common data structures for implementing a priority queue are
那一般实现优先队列的数据结构是
A heap, a min heap.
堆  一个最小堆
So I have to make sure that I'm actually doing this operation.
但我要确保有进行这个操作
I can't just change it and not affect my heap.
我不能为了不影响我的堆 而修改它
So, there is an implicit operation going on there.
所以 这里有一个隐含的操作
OK, now I repeat.
现在重复一次
I find the cheapest thing,
找到权值最小的边
oh, and I also have to set, now,
同时我们还要
a pointer from each of these guys back to u.
设置一些指针 从这些顶点指回u
So here, this guy sets a pointer going this way.
所以这个顶点 要设一个指针指回去
This guy sets a pointer going this way,
这个顶点设一个指针指回去
and this guy sets a pointer going this way.
还有这个顶点设一个指针指回去
That's my pi thing that's going to keep track of
这是π函数要追踪的
who caused me to set my value to what it is.
促使我把键值设为新键值的顶点
So now, we go in and we find the cheapest thing, again.
现在回到队列里 找最便宜的点
And we're going to do it fast, too.
而且我们要做得快一点
OK, this is a fast algorithm.
这是一个快速算法
OK, so now we're going to go do this again.
现在要再进行同样的步骤
So now, what's the cheapest thing to extract?
现在要取出的最便宜的是哪一个？
This guy here, right? So, we'll take him out,
这个顶点 是吧？将它取出来
OK, and now we update all of his neighbors.
然后更新它的邻接顶点
So this guy gets five.
这个顶点变为5
This guy gets 12.
这个顶点是12
This guy gets nine.
这个顶点是9
This guy we don't update. We don't update him
这个不用更新 不用更新它
because he's no longer in the priority queue.
因为它不再是优先队列里的元素
And all of these guys now,
所有这些顶点
we make pointer where they're supposed to point to.
设置指针指向它们应该指向的地方
And, we're done with that step.
这一步就完成了
Now we find the cheapest one.
现在继续找权值最小的
What's the cheapest one now?
现在哪个是最小的？
The five over here. Good. So, we take him out.
这个5 很好 将它带走
OK, we update the neighbors.
再更新它的邻居
Here, yep, that goes to six now.
这里 没错 现在变为6
And, we have that pointer.
还有一个指针
And, this guy we don't do, because he's not in there.
这个顶点不更新 因为它不在队列里
This guy becomes 14, and this guy here becomes eight.
这个顶点变为14 还有这个变为8
So, we update that guy, make him be eight.
更新这个顶点 变为8
Did I do this the right way?
我有木有做错喔？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
[Prof]:Yeah, because pi is a function of this guy.
[教授]:对 因为π是这个顶点的一个函数
So basically, this thing, then, disappears. Yeah,
所以基本上 这些就会消失了
did I have another one that I missed?
我是不是错过了一个点？
12, yes, good, it's removed,
12 对 很好 把它移走
OK, because pi is just a function.
因为π只是一个函数
And now I'm OK. OK, so now what do I do?
现在完成了 现在要做什么？
OK, so now my set, A, consists of these three things,
现在我的集合A 包括了这三项
and now I want the cheapest edge.
现在我要权值最小的边
I know it's in the minimum spanning tree.
我知道它会在最小生成树里
So let me just greedily pick it.
所以贪心地选择它
So what's the cheapest thing now?
现在哪个是最小的？
This guy u here? Yeah, six.
这里这个？对 是6
So we take it. We go to update these things,
带它走 然后再更新这些顶点
and nothing matters here.
已经没有相关的顶点了
OK, nothing changes because these guys are already in A.
没什么好改变的了 因为这些都已经在A里
OK, so now the cheapest one is eight here.
所以现在最便宜的是这里的8
Good. So, we take eight out.
好的 把8取出来
OK, we update this. Nothing to be done.
更新这个点 什么都不用做
This: nothing to be done.
这个点：什么都不用做
This: oh, no, this one, instead of 14 we can make this be three.
这个顶点 噢不 它要把14换成3
So, we get rid of that pointer and make it point that way.
去掉这个指针 让它指向这边
Now three is the cheapest thing.
现在3是最便宜的
So, we take it out,
将它取出来
and of course there's nothing to be done over there.
当然 这边已经没有什么好更新的了
And now, last, I take nine. And it's done.
现在 最后取走9 完成了
And 15: it's done. And the algorithm terminates.
还有15 完成了 这样算法就结束了
OK, and as I look at, now, all the edges that I picked,
现在正如看到的 所有我选择的边
those are exactly all the edges that we had at the beginning.
正是一开始的那些边
Let's do an analysis here.
这里做一下分析
OK, so let's see, this part here costs me order V, right?
看这里 这一部分花费O(V) 是吧？
OK, and this part,
还有这部分
let's see what we are doing here. We gonna do this part...
看看我们这里做了啥 我们这部分...
Well, we're going to go through this loop how many times?
嗯嗯 我们做了这个循环多少次
V times.
V次
It's V elements we put into the queue.
有V个元素放进队列里
We are not inserting anything. We're just taking them out.
没有进行任何插入 只是将它们取出来
This goes V times,
所以这是|V|次
OK, and we do a certain number of extract Mins.
然后还有几个取出最小值操作
So, we're going to do order V extract Mins.
所以 我们要O(V)次取出最小值
And then we go to the adjacency list,
然后到了邻接表
and we have some constant things.
有一些常值的操作
But we have these implicit decreased keys for this stuff here.
但这里还有一些隐含的降低键值的操作
That's this thing here.
也就是这里
OK, and so how many implicit decreased keys do we have?
有多少隐含的降低键值操作？
That's going to be the expensive thing.
这将会是昂贵的开销
OK, we have, in this case, the degree of u of those.
在这个情况里 有u的度那么多
so overall, how many implicit decreased keys do we have?
所以 总共有多少隐含的降低键值的操作？
Well, we have V times through.
我们总共有V的时间
How big could the degree of u be?
u的度可能有多大？
OK, it could be as big as V, order V.
它可能和V一样大 O(V)
So, that's V^2 decreased use.
所以是V^2次降低操作
But we can do a better bound than that.
但我们能找出一个更好的上限
How many do we really have?
实际上有多少？
Yeah, at most order E,
没错 最多是O(E)
OK, because what am I doing?
因为我做了什么？
I'm summing up the degrees of all the vertices.
我把所有顶点的度加起来
That's how many times I actually execute that.
那就是实际的执行次数
So, I have order E, implicit decreased keys.
所以是O(E)个隐含的降低键值
So the time overall is order V times
所以总共的时间是O(V)乘以
time for whatever the extract Min is
取出最小值所需的时间
plus E times the time for decreased key.
加上E乘以降低键值的时间
So now, let's look at data structures,
现在 我们再看数据结构
and we can evaluate for different data structures
在不同的数据结构下做评估
what this formula gives us.
看看这条公式会变成怎样
So, we have different ways of implementing a data structure.
我们有不同的方式来实现这个数据结构
We have the cost of extract Min,
我们有取出最小值的开销
and of decreased key, and total.
有降低键值的开销 还有总开销
So, the simplest way of implementing a data structure
实现这个数据结构的最简单方法
is an unsorted array.
是一个无序数组
If I have an unsorted array,
对于一个无序数组
how much time does it take me to extract the minimum element?
我要花费多少时间来取出最小元素？
If I have an unsorted array?
如果是无序数组的话？
order V in this case because it's an array of size V.
是O(V) 因为它是一个大小为V的数组
And, to do a decreased key,
还有降低键值操作
OK, I can do it in order one.
我可以在O(1)时间内完成
So, the total is V^2, good,
所以总共是O(V^2) 很好
order V^2 algorithm.
O(V^2)的算法
Or, as people suggested, how about a binary heap?
或者用人民喜闻乐见的二叉堆怎么样？
to do an extract Min in a binary heap will cost me what?
从二叉堆里取最小值的开销是多少？
O of log V. Decreased key will cost me,
O(log V)  那降低键值呢？
yeah, it turns out you can do that in order log V
没错 答案是可以在O(log V)里完成
because basically you just have to shuffle the value,
因为基本上只需要把修改的值向上渗透 【译注：教授此处应该口误把sift(渗透操作)说成shuffle(洗牌操作)了】
actually shuffle it up towards the root, OK?
实际上 是向根渗透操作
O of log V. And, the total cost therefore is?
所以是O(log V) 那总开销是？
E log V, good.
O(E log V)
Which of these is better?
哪一个比较好？
It depends, good.
看情况 有见地
When is one better, and when is the other better?
那什么时候这个更好 什么时候另一个更好？
Yeah?
你说？
[Student]:Inaudible.
[学生]：……
[Prof]:if it's a dense graph,
[教授]:如果是一个稠密图
E is close to V^2, the array is better.
E近似等于V^2 用数组比较好
But if it's a sparse graph,
但如果是一个稀疏图
and E is much smaller than V^2,
E远小于V^2
then the binary heap is better.
那么二叉堆会比较好
So that motivated the invention of a data structure,
这催生了一种新的数据结构
OK, called a Fibonacci Heap.
称为菲波那契堆
So, Fibonacci Heap is covered in Chapter 20 of CLRS.
菲波那契堆在书的第20章会有全面介绍
We're not going to hold you responsible for the content,
我们不要求掌握这部分内容
but it's an interesting data structure
但它是一种很有意思的数据结构
because it's an amortized data structure.
因为它是一种平摊数据结构
And it turns out that it is data structure,
事实证明 这种数据结构
you can do extract Min in order log V amortized time.
你可以在O(log V)的平摊时间内取出最小值
And remarkably, you can do decreased key in order one amortized.
更酷炫的是 你能在O(1)平摊时间内降低键值
So, when I plug those in, what do I get over here?
那么把它们加起来会是多少？
What's that going to be? Plug that it here.
将会是多少？在这里加起来
It's going to be V times log V plus E: E plus V log V.
它将会是V乘以log V  加上E + V log V
These are amortized, so what's this?
这些是平摊的 那这是什么？
Trick question. It's worst-case.
恶作剧之问 它其实是最坏情况
It's not amortized over here.
这里不是平摊的
These are amortized, but that's the beauty of amortization.
这些是平摊的 这就是平摊性之美
I can say it's going to be worst case: E plus V log V over here,
它是最坏情况下的开销 E + V log V
because when I add up the amortized cost of my operations,
因为把操作的平摊花销加起来
it's an upper bound on the true costs.
得出的是实际开销的上限
OK, so as I say,
正如我所说的
one of the beauties of this amortized analysis,
这就是平摊分析之美
and in particular, being able to assign
尤其是 它还能够
different costs to different operations is
为不同操作分配不同的花费
I can just add them up and I get my worst-case costs.
我只需将它们加起来 就能得到最坏情况代价
So this is already V log V.
这里已经是V log V了
There are a couple other algorithms just before I let you go.
在下课前 再提一下一些其它的算法
Kruskal's Algorithm in the book
书里的Kruskal算法
uses another amortized data structure
它使用另一种平摊数据结构
called a disjoint set data structure,
称为不相交集合数据结构
which also runs in E log V, that is, this time:
同样也花费E log V 也就是这个时间
runs in this time, the same as using a binary heap.
运行时间是这个 和二叉堆一样
So, I'll refer you to the book.
我可以告诉你们 在书里面
The best algorithm to date with this problem is
处理这个问题的最好算法是
done by our own David Karger on the faculty here
由我们学校教员中的David Karger
with one of our former graduates, Phil Kline,
和我们校友Phil Kline一起完成的
who is now a professor at Brown, and Robert Tarjan,
现在他在布朗大学当教授 还有Robert Tarjan
who is sort of like the master of all data structures
他差不多是所有数据结构的砖家
who was a professor at Princeton in 1993.
他在1993年时 还是普林斯顿的教授
it's a randomized algorithm,
那是一个随机算法
and it gives you order V plus E expected time.
它的期望时间是O(V+E)
OK, so that's the best to date.
那也是当今最好的算法
It's still open as to whether there is a deterministic,
它对这一类问题也是友好的 如是否有确定性...
there is worst-case bound,
是否有一个最坏情况上限
whether there is a worst-case bound that is linear time.
是否存在一个是线性时间的最坏情况上限
OK, but there is a randomized linear time,
好的 对随机化的数据有线性的时间
and otherwise, this is essentially the best bound
否则 这就会是最好的上界了
without additional assumptions.
如果没有别的假设的话
OK, very cool stuff.
非常酷炫啊
Next, we're going to see a lot of these ideas of
下节课 我们将会看到很多的
greedy and dynamic programming in practice.
贪心算法和动态编程的应用